<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remarks, and animadversions, on Mr. Keith's two sermons, being his first after ordiantion, [sic] preached at the parish church of St. George's Butolphs-Lane, London, May the 12th. 1700. on St. Luke i. 6 Now impartially compared with his former writings, setting George against Keith, and endeavouring to reconcile them, by shewing what he should have said upon the subjest. By W.B. a communicant of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>W. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76517</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B224</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230841</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899691</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899691</idno>
            <idno type="VID">134553</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76517)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 134553)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2417:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Remarks, and animadversions, on Mr. Keith's two sermons, being his first after ordiantion, [sic] preached at the parish church of St. George's Butolphs-Lane, London, May the 12th. 1700. on St. Luke i. 6 Now impartially compared with his former writings, setting George against Keith, and endeavouring to reconcile them, by shewing what he should have said upon the subjest. By W.B. a communicant of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>W. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author; and sold by the booksellers of London and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Keith, George, 1639?-1716 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:134553:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:134553:1"/>
            <p>REMARKS, AND <hi>Animadverſions,</hi> On Mr. <hi>Keith</hi>'s Two Sermons, Being his Firſt after Ordiantion, Preached at the Pariſh Church of St. <hi>George</hi>'s <hi>Butolphs-Lane, London, May</hi> the 12th. 1700. On St. <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>KE</hi> i. 6. Now Impartially compared with his former Writings, SETTING <hi>George</hi> Againſt <hi>Keith.</hi> And Endeavouring to Reconcile them, By ſhewing what he ſhould have ſaid upon the Subject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> W. B. <hi>a Communicant of the Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the AUTHOR; and Sold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:134553:2"/>
            <head>Remarks and Animadverſions on Mr. <hi>Keith</hi>'s Two Sermons.</head>
            <p>SINCE I underſtand that the late Reverend, tho' as yet not Right Reverend <hi>George Keith,</hi> has entered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church as Jackdaws into the Steeple to build, and hatch there; entering almoſt undeſired by any: ſo for ought I know may dye unlamented: For I believe that the Church (as the Apoſtles did) will not go to Prayers for ſuch an other to ſucceed, and ſupply in his place; I never heard that the preſent Church had, or uſed any ſuch cuſtom, tho' it was common among the Churches of God in the days of old. I am not inſenſible that that upſtart <hi>Prelate,</hi> which whether out of fear, or trouble, or both, has done that Outwardly, which I have ſome reaſon to think he Inwardly deteſts, ſince this his <hi>Sermon</hi> was not a Recantation of his former Errors, which are manifeſtly extant in his former Scriblings, which as I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand he has neither Cryed down in Church, nor Market, nor cauſed to be Burnt by the Hands of the Common Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; but are left us ſtill upon Record as Authentick: So that it makes me, and ſome others think, that his Judgment differs from his preſent Undertakings, having but clattered <hi>Gideons</hi> Rams-Horns and broken Pitchers together, ſo as to affright his Conſcience, and baiſting it for being Scittiſh, has made even an <hi>Aſs</hi> of it, by cauſing the poor Jade to carry a Steeple which it formerly hated: and all this becauſe Brown Bread is better than no White. All wiſe People do think that ſuch an one ſhould have given ſome Satisfaction to the Church in general, which he had forſaken, and formerly ſo abuſed; he might, and ſhould then have told the People, that he came there to give ſatisfaction more than to receive any; and ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf there not for Worth, or notorious Wickedneſs; but for Weakneſs, in not diſcerning and following all the Commands and Ordinances which are Truths. If he had gone on, and humbly craved a fair Conſtruction, and favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Acception; Firſt of his Offences paſt, that his readineſs to acknowledge them might paſs for one degree of Satisfaction, and his ſuddain Recantation for an other; ſo what was want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Ripeneſs, ſhould be ſupplied in Sincerity. But ſince none of this was heard to come from his Mouth, but only the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:134553:2"/>
choice of a good Text, which he ſo mangled and tore, that the ſharpeſt Eye could not ſo diſcern as to know what it was amongſt all the <hi>Tautologies,</hi> and Impertinent, or Nonſenſical ſtuff, which by hard and long driving he forced from it; which made, it ſeems, ſome well-meaning <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to get ſome in Commiſſion to ſend an <hi>Hue-and-Cry</hi> aftert he forelorn Text, ſo as to overtake, arreſt, and make the beſt of it; which I am aſſured was done for the Honour and Reputation of the New Convert, and the languiſhing Church which he pretends to be a Member of. But in my weak judgment, any that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakes his firſt or ſecond Love, can, or will Never be true to his Third.</p>
            <p>So having ſeen the <hi>Poſt-Boy, May</hi> the 14th. which pretended to give the Subſtance of the Sermons: And on <hi>May</hi> 16. meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with an <hi>Advertiſement,</hi> in which the now Holderforth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payed not only the <hi>Poſt-Boy,</hi> but Mr. <hi>Brodford</hi> a Printer alſo in the currant Coin of <hi>Billingsgate;</hi> which made me the more curious to inquire after his Former Pieces; the <hi>Poſt-Boy,</hi> and his Initiating (which I judge ſhould have been his Recantation) Sermons, not of ſome but all his former Errors and Miſtakes, whether wilfully, or ignorantly committed. So having mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered ſo many as I could get together, I took the boldneſs upon me to compare them, and ſo Remark on the Sermons: Now ſince the Printer has left us Two Blank Pages, the reaſon of which, as I conjecture, is becauſe the <hi>Poſt-Boy</hi> has ſupplied us with Matter which they ſhould have contained, being as was obſerved ſuch as did, and doth naturally flow from the New Prophet: but like the Bears young Ones (being now releaſed from the Tautological <hi>I ſays</hi>) in time Licked into Shape and Form. For if you read the <hi>Poſt-Boy,</hi> with his opening of the Words, and compare them, they are the ſame; only ſome Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions are made, which the Printer has forgot to tell us of, as he did in the Farewel Farce: For <hi>pag.</hi> 6. he tells us by Tautolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, as the <hi>Poſt-Man</hi> doth, <hi>That Hypocrites are righteous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Men, tho' not righteous before God:</hi> and that <hi>walking</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies <hi>journying,</hi> and <hi>travelling forward;</hi> only by a little Licking, he has changed the Words, viz. <hi>(travelling forward)</hi> into that Phraſe <hi>going forward,</hi> by progreſſive motion, which amounts to a Tautology. And <hi>pag.</hi> 8. by <hi>Ordinances</hi> are underſtood all <hi>the Ceremonial Precepts,</hi> &amp;c. called in <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.1. <hi>Ordinances of Service pertaining to the Temple:</hi> Which Text, and denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I ſuppoſe the <hi>Poſt-Boy</hi> having only left out, being no Textuary, or caring to meddle with Holy Things. Now the Obſervations he makes from the words thus opened are Three, from pag. 9. to 14. <hi>Firſt, the State of the Jewiſh Church at
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:134553:3"/>
that time to which the Text relates, was very corrupt, for ſome did not believe one Fundamental Doctrine; others put falſe gloſſes on the Scriptures,</hi> Matt. 15.3, 6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Others had Practices corrupt, and contrary to what they taught: there were Sons of</hi> Belial, <hi>and Rebels,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Alas this, and more has this ſelf-ſame <hi>Demas</hi> ſaid of the now eſtabliſhed Church, without any Recantation, as appears from his former Books, viz. <hi>The Way caſt up,</hi> pag. 36. <hi>I cannot,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in the leaſt acknowledge that ever any National Church can be a true Church of Chriſt (ſince they are a mixed and confuſed rabble of Godleſs Atheiſts) it were wiſhed that this, and all others were true. But men ſhould not make ſuch prepoſterous haſte to make National Churches by meer humane Laws and Power: bare humane Laws, Edicts, and Decrees will never do it; for indeed this hath been the ground and riſe of all Perſecutions,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For thoſe that will have a National Church, will have all others to bow and joyn with them; and is always a Perſecuting Church, (its her very Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) ſo muſt always be exceeding Hypocritical, ſeeing ſhe begetteth Thouſands to be her Children, and Members by meer Will and Power of Man, which only makes Hypocrites.</hi> And for the <hi>Teachers,</hi> he further ſaith, pag. 40, 41, 42. <hi>That they have been generally, and for the moſt part, ſelf-ſeeking, worldly-minded, and covetous men, who loved Pleaſure and Riches more than God; and this the Magiſtrates did well know, and ſaw the beſt way to prevent, was to Bribe them with Augmentations, and Benefices. The Preachers of the</hi> Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes <hi>were Lay-men moſt of them, and wrought with their Hands, as the Teachers of the Primitive Church did, and had no Stipends, or Salleries, but Preached freely.</hi> And <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Rev.</hi> pag. 30, 31. <hi>Altho' the School-men and National Teachers Doctrine, who generally being men void of all ſenſe or feeling of God, have in the blindneſs of their minds, and in the wiſdom from below, which is carnal, earthly, and deviliſh, framed and invented this perverſe Doctrine for their own gains and ends.</hi> And pag. 136. He tells us, <hi>That the Church is an Habitation for Ravenous Beaſts and Owls,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And down muſt all the proud lording, lofty Clergy, with their many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Doctorſhip, Lordſhip, and Maſterſhip.</hi> And aſſures us that it lay upon him from the Lord, and ſo bids all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:134553:3"/>
others <hi>To depart from theſe Teachers which cannot point to the knowledge of the living God:</hi> Nay, further, in his <hi>Rector Corrected,</hi> pag. 122, 123, 124. <hi>Is not the Popiſh Church thy Grandmother? who hath taught this deſtruction of Layick, and Clegy, Secular, and Spiritual; for theſe ſhe only calleth Clergy, or Spiritual, who are either Prieſts, or Biſhops, or Popes, or in ſome ſuch order the reſt Laicks or Secular, whereas as the Apoſtle calleth the whole Body of the People the Clergy, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of the Lord; have they leſs then of the Spiritual, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are Mechanicks? And have ye (that call your ſelves the Clergy) more, becauſe ye underſtand the Tongues, and walk in Long Robes, and love the chief Places in Aſſemblies, and are called Maſters?</hi> Again, <hi>Are not ſuch of the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>made Miniſtry ambitious? Do they not affect great Titles? Or if it be a ſin to affect them, is it not becauſe they are vain, and ſinful? Have not ſome of the Clergy (ſo called) greater Titles now, than the Rabbies had of Old? as, Your Grace, Your Holineſs, Moſt Reverend Father in God, Right Reverend,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus far <hi>George</hi> has been and is ſo poſſitive in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State of our National Church, that it's as corrupt both in Doctrine and Manners, as ever the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church was in <hi>Zachariah</hi>'s time.</p>
            <p>Now comes <hi>Keith,</hi> and grants the ſame, making in <hi>pag.</hi> 13. only this Suppoſition, <hi>If they be ſuch, we muſt not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Aſſembling our ſelves (as</hi> Zacharias <hi>did) publickly with them.</hi> Whenas <hi>George</hi> ſaith, <hi>We muſt depart from them:</hi> Which is an Even and Equal Match, One againſt One; namely <hi>George</hi> againſt <hi>Keith.</hi> But alas, to <hi>George</hi>'s aſſiſtance comes without any blowing of his Horn, the Noyſie <hi>Poſt-Man</hi> with his Tautologies, and Impertinent Quotations of Nonſenſe, and Texts of Scripture, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.13. and <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.4, 5. which tells us that theſe, even almoſt a Regiment of Foot, viz. <hi>Jeſhua</hi> and <hi>Bani, Kadmiel, Shebaniah, Bunni, Sherebiah, Bani</hi> and <hi>Chenani,</hi> &amp;c. ſtood upon the Stairs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—Now <hi>Keith</hi> well knowing that two to one are odds at Foot-ball, ſo for Peace-ſaith, as the rude <hi>Poſt-Man</hi> had ſaid, as appears in pag. 14, 15. ſetting down <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29, 13. and <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.4, &amp; 5. only get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting leave not to call over all the Muſter-Roll, but to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:134553:4"/>
ſtop with an <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at <hi>Bani,</hi> and to ſleep in an whole Skin; he's content with Pottage thrice hot, provided he may but have ſo much Meat as he can take out of the Pot with his Fleſh-Fork; he cares not whether out of Knowledge, Malice or Ignorance, if you call him <hi>Prieſt,</hi> as pag. 18. Tho' <hi>George</hi> ſaith, <hi>Its an odious and abominable Name;</hi> as <hi>Imed. Rev.</hi> p. 136. Now by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Aftertoon Harangue, the Fray begins again between <hi>George</hi> and <hi>Keith,</hi> ſince the <hi>Rabbi</hi> hath ſaid, p. 21. <hi>That the Church under the Old Teſtament was not carnal.</hi> Whenas <hi>George</hi> in the places before-cited, hath aſſured us, <hi>not only that under the Old Teſtament it was (but alſo all National Churches whatſoever both were, and are) carnal, and not to be joyned with.</hi> But I find by our Young Maſter's words, that ſince there were ſome among the <hi>Jews,</hi> who profeſſed to have know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Law and divine Myſteries, ſo gathered <hi>Diſciples</hi> and <hi>Proſelites</hi> to them, whom they taught apart; and for that were called <hi>Rabbies,</hi> as pag. 11. This as he hints there, he has a mind to do; Nay, further, ſince in p. 25. 26. he ſaith, <hi>That as in the Jewiſh Church there were great Faults both in the Rulers of it, and the People alſo, yet the true Prophets did not ſeperate from them, but reproved and repreſented them to the Government, which eſtabliſhed the Church.</hi> By which is covertly hinted, that he being a true Prophet, deſigns fairly at ſome time or other, to repreſent the Errors and Miſcarriages of all the Church to the Supream Governours; ſo that here's fair Warning; Have at ye Sirs, for he's reſolued to ſtick to the Church, he'll en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to have it cleanſed. So in my judgment there's more danger of <hi>Keith</hi> than of <hi>George:</hi> But ſince <hi>George,</hi> the <hi>Poſt-Boy,</hi> and ſome others, have maliciouſly ſuggeſted and report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that <hi>Keith,</hi> as pag. 29. has put himſelf into the Prieſts Office <hi>for a Piece of Bread.</hi> Now to paſs over the reſt of the Fulſome and Impertinent Stuff, being weary of Remarking, I am at laſt reſolved to take poor <hi>Keith</hi>'s part, and endeavour if poſſible to reconcile them; for I am well informed, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that he did not put himſelf into Orders for one piece of Bread, <hi>but for whole Loaves; Lumps of Money,</hi> or <hi>Steeple upon Steeple. George,</hi> I would and will not have my Friend <hi>Keith</hi> thus undervalued; and ſeeing you were formerly Friends and Brethren in Iniquity, being falſe Prophets, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 3. which taught the People to go aſtray, you now are puniſhable, as <hi>pag.</hi> 30. unleſs you make Satisfaction; for tho' you have a Tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration by our Laws, yet the Laws of God will not excuſe you. So be ſure that the next Oration you make to the People, to ſtick to the <hi>Text,</hi> and tell them as I have, or if I had time, ſincerely for your and the Churches good, would have told what all the <hi>Commands</hi> and <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> are to be ſo obſerved, as to be Blameleſs.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:134553:4"/>
            <head>Afternoon Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LUKE i. 6.</hi>
                  </bibl> And they were both Righteous, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all the Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord blameleſs.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HAving in my foregoing Diſcourſe in the Words of the Text, <hi>firſt</hi> ſhewn you what the True Faith and Church is, and where found; <hi>ſecondly,</hi> what that Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is, which makes any Blameleſs. So 3dly, and <hi>laſtly,</hi> I come now to declare what the <hi>Commands</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> were, and are. The <hi>Commands</hi> (beſides thoſe 10 which are called the Moral Law, which our Lord and Saviour came to fulfil, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.17.) are not many, however, whoſoever ſhall ſhall break one of the leaſt Commandments, and ſhall teach Men ſo, he ſhall be the leaſt, and guilty of the breach of the whole, <hi>James</hi> 2.10. Our Lord, the wiſe and good Lawgiver, to take the Scandal and Folly of the Old Law, which the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> had put upon it by their falſe gloſſes, the firſt of which he takes notice of, was that mentioned by St. <hi>Matthew</hi> 5.43. where he ſaith, <hi>It hath been ſaid, thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour, and hate thine Enemy:</hi> And verſ. 44. <hi>But I ſay unto you, love your Enemies:</hi> Which as St. <hi>John</hi> 13.34. tells us, our bleſſed Lord calls a New Commandment; which ſame Evangeliſt tells us in his 1 Epiſt. <hi>John</hi> 3.7. was a Meſſage even from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as old as either the Law of Nature or <hi>Moſes</hi>'s: but as moſt of the Ancients conceive this Commandment of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's was termed New, being an <hi>Hebraiſm,</hi> it therefore muſt (as one of the Fathers ſaith) be accounted moſt excellent of all, or a rare, choiſe, and ſpecial one, <hi>unum prae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> omnibus unum</hi> (i. e.) One above all others; and as Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> Paraphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon it, ſaith, Chriſt would have us perpetually mindful of that, as if it were a Law newly enacted: For we (ſaith he) know that Laws at the firſt making of them are carefully looked into, and diligently obſerved; but by degrees wear out of Mens Memory, and in the end grows into diſuſe: And for that end Chriſt recommended this as a New Commandment, and being alſo propounded in a new Form. For in the Law it run thus, <hi>Love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf;</hi> but in the Goſpel, <hi>Love one another as I have loved you;</hi> that is in ſome caſe more than your ſelves. Now a Law may be ſaid to be New, out of a double conſideration, <hi>firſt,</hi> either in reſpect of the thing commanded, if it be ſuch a thing as before never fell under any Law, which cauſed the Proverb, <hi>Novus Rex nova lex,</hi> New Lords, New Laws; becauſe or for the moſt part new Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:134553:5"/>
or Rulers, bring in New Cuſtoms, proclaim New E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts, and ſettle New Orders in Church or State: Or <hi>ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> in reſpect of the New Act of Commanding: So an Old Statute when its revived, an Old Book reprinted, an Old Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion laid aſide for a long time and again taken up, may be called a New One. So that in both theſe reſpects the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand may be ſaid to be New. So to love our Enemies, is <hi>firſt,</hi> to wiſh and deſire; and 2dly, to do well to them: for to think well of and towards another, to wiſh and deſire their welfare is the Soul, and to do them that Good which is wiſhed them is all the Body, of real and true Love, which muſt and will expreſs it ſelf variouſly according to the different conditions of its object, and the divers degres of its own power; for if the thing loved be very good, then Love is to put on the Garment of Gladneſs, and is delighted in it; if it be in very bad eſtate, and deſtitute of good, then Love is to turn into Pity to commiſſerate: If it be unable to help, then it ſtays in Deſires and good Wiſhes: but if it has any power, it exerts it, and goes into Action to be Blameleſs. Now its manifeſt that the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> or they Pharaſaically inclined, wholly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heared to the Traditions of the Elders, and the Opinions of their Doctors and Rabbies; for their Carriage was ſuch, as ſhewed they thought themſelves not only permitted, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to deſire and do Evil to their Enemies, and all were ſuch in their eſteem, who were not <hi>Jews</hi> or Proſelites: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they denyed them common Offices of Civility; yea, would not ſo much as direct a Stranger in his Way, if he were out of their Religion; and beſides, called them by moſt unci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Names, ſuch as Dogs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in paying them by Fraud or Violence: I could heartily wiſh that none of the Spawn were to be found now amongſt us; but to my Shame be it ſpoken, ſuch was I formerly, but now thanks be to God, I am waſhed and cleanſed from ſuch Pollutions; and for the future will endeavour to obſerve and keep this New Commandment to be Blameleſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Subſtance then of that New Command, as I humbly conceive is in my thoughts (to love our Enemies) not that we ſhould love any thing that is Evil to us, and tends to our Ruin as ſuch; nor that we ſhould not endeavour and take the beſt and likelieſt Ways to free our ſelves from a bad eſtate; nor that we ſhould not do and deſire ſome Evil to Men, who may be our Enemies, provided that it be in order to a greater Good than its Depravation of to themſelves, or others, and not inconſiſtent with their Happineſs: but that we deſire, and do as much as we can of good to them, who deſigns and does the worſt Evils to us: For <hi>firſt,</hi> conſider that tho' they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:134553:5"/>
are our Enemies, yet by their evil deſign we may often be the better for them, tho' they may intend no leſs than our ruin, as ſome did mine formerly, yet it often proves our Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; yea, the very Blow by which they would kill, often cures, ſo that the Sword becomes a Lancet; and the Enemy which deſigns to make Wounds, proves a Chirurgion, and heals them. True, this being beſides their Intention, we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may think they do not merit our Love or Thanks the more: but ſince they prove Inſtruments of Good to us, we ſhould and muſt love the Cauſe, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did: Why ſhould not we then as well love thoſe that do us good againſt their Wills, as thoſe that do it without any Will at all? tho' they have many evil Deſigns, and miſchievous Devices againſt us, yet theſe do but make us more cautious and circumſpect, more exact in what we ſay and do than otherwiſe we would be; which is a Spur to make us do our beſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Friends are often ſo blinded with Paſſion, that they can ſee nothing that is amiſs in us; nay, if ſome had fewer Friends, and more Enemies, they had been much better then they are: Therefore we muſt love Enemies as we do Poyſons that are mixt by a learned and careful Phyſitian, being made ſoveraign Medicines to cure our Diſeaſes. 2dly, Tho' they are our Enemies, and do evil to us, yet there is ſome good in them; let us love them then for the ſake of it, and imitate our Maker: its but juſt that we proſecute and deſtroy the Wickedneſs of any, but let us ſpare and ſave the Creature, for its God's Image. Phyſitians do never cut off any part of the Body, which is ſo corrupted, until there is no hopes of a Cure: And in the Body Politick, its certain that the relatives of an Offender are not involved in his Sufferings, where the offence is not very great: nor then unleſs it can be ſuppoſed that they were Partners with him; or it be neceſſary for the Publick, and greater Good, both to demonſtrate a greater Severity againſt ſuch Crimes, as thereby to terrify Men, and alſo to engage all Relations to concern themſelves in one anothers well doing; like to this ſhould our carriage be to thoſe that hate us. Pray are there no hopes that the Evils may be removed from the Lives and Minds of the Perſon without their ruine? Try if there are: Nay, 'tis hard to ſay that any are ſo much our Enemies, that they will never be our Friends: God may and can turn their Hearts. 3dly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt never do any Evil which will make it impoſſible for our Enemies to be happy; they are vital parts, which muſt in no wiſe be cut off, unleſs the caſe is very deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. True, they are Men liable to Errors, but yet (as I was) capable of Information: they are God's Image, and our Fleſh and Bone, let us not be angry with them if they have hitherto loitered, and comes to be hired at the Ninth Hour: Let us
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:134553:6"/>
imitate our Lord and Maſter, and (as he has loved us) ſo love one another; and reward them as well for one Hour, as if they had laboured all the Day. Yet what if our Enemies be Infidels, evil and fooliſh, or no Chriſtians, having put off common Civility and Humanity? verily the greater than is their Miſery: but ſince they are not Devils, being as I was, capable of a recovery, the more compaſſionable are their caſe, therefore to be pittied; for its unnatural Cruelty, monſtrous Inhumanity and helliſh Malice, to hate and proſecute any in Miſery; What if they be our Enemies? they are Friends to many others as good if not better than our ſelves; and can't we be ſatisfied with, and love that which is our particular Intereſt, if others receive Advantage by it: For if the Rain that overflows me, makes my Neighbours Field fruitful, I ought not to (and muſt not) diſlike it: or if the Sun warms thouſands by its heat, and ſcorches me, or the Seaſon by which I ſuffer, favours many others, I am not to be diſpleaſed: we are all God's People, and Sheep of his Paſture, therefore we have the greateſt engagement laid upon us to mutual Kindneſs and Good-will; nay, that <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Virtue is more innocent, and doth leſs harm to both our ſelves and others; and as we find by ſweet experience, ordinarily prevails upon others to lay aſide all malicious thoughts: for we are naturally prone to imitate, as with the Froward to learn Frowardneſs, and with the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Love; and further, there's no reaſon imaginable to hate one that loves us, becauſe we only hate that which is evil to us; but if any Perſon love us, we can't think he doth us evil, ſince he deſigns and will do us good: ſo that if we hate ſuch, we hate our own good. To conclude this Command, our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning Love for Hatred, quencheth the violence of it: for the common Obſervation is, if the Sun ſhine upon the Fire, it will put it out: ſo Love takes away the Heat and Fewel from thoſe unnatural and conſuming Fires, deſtroying both the Parent and Nurſe of Enmity, <hi>viz.</hi> Hatred and Evil, which would have propagated and preſerved it; yea, this is the firm Foundation of a laſting Peace, even that which paſſes our Underſtanding, obtaining an anſwer to all our Petitions, by forgiving as we would be forgiven; and as St. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.22. ſaith, <hi>Then whatſoever we ask we ſhall receive of him, becauſe we keep his Commandments, and do thoſe things that are pleaſing in his ſight:</hi> And theſe are his Commandments, to believe on Jeſus Chriſt, and love one another, even our Enemies, as he gave us Commandment ſo as to be Blameleſs. The Second Commandment which our Saviour gave his Apoſtles, is mentioned by St. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20. <hi>All Power is given unto me in Heaven and Earth. Go ye therefore and teach</hi> (that is to make Diſciples) <hi>all Nations, Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>teaching them to obſerve all Things whatſoever I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:134553:6"/>
you,</hi> &amp;c. In which Words our Saviour firſt Aſſerts, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares his own Commiſſion, ſhewing his Apoſtles that what he did was not the reſult of his own private Judgment, but the Exerciſe of Authority which was given him of his Father; who had confirmed unto him a full Power of ordering, and diſpoſing whatſoever belonged to the Church. But ſince in his own Perſon he muſt Aſcend and leave them: he gave them their Deputation by ſending the Holy Spirit the Comforter to be with, and Comfort them to the end of the World: And ſince they were Mortal, he gave them Power to Depute others to ſucceed them in them ſame Care, and to deliver down the ſame Power ſucceſſively to the end of the World; it's then without doubt by that Promiſe that our Saviour intended ſome Benefits to the Church, which ſhould be of no leſs continuance than it ſelf: So the Apoſtles were to be the firſt Diſpenſers of thoſe Benefits: Now the Benefits as appears from the Commiſſion were theſe theſe, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Teaching, <hi>Secondly,</hi> Baptiſing, and ſome other Things which he had Commanded, as the Taking and Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Bread, and Drinking the Cup, which was to be a ſhewing of his Death to the end of the World: And the Exerciſing Cenſures againſt the Obſtinate and Sinful, ſuch as <hi>Elimas</hi> the Sorcerer, as <hi>Act</hi> 13. &amp;c. Now Theſe were either to end with the Apoſtles, or they were not, if they were then to end: The Church ever ſince their Deaths has been with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch, which amounts only to this, that there has been no Church ſince their Deceaſe. Or if they did not end with the Apoſtles, but have always been, and are ſtill to be exerciſed unto the end of the World: then there ever muſt have been, and now muſt be fit Perſons: Which like to the Apoſtles, muſt have a juſt Power to diſpenſe theſe Benefits, or exerciſe theſe Offices; for no leſs can be conceived to have been intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt in his Promiſe, of being with his Church to the end. Now when the great Biſhop of our Souls ordained his Apoſtles, it was according to the Tenor of his own Ordination, <hi>As my Father ſent me ſo ſend I you,</hi> Luke 4.18. And ſaid <hi>John</hi> 23.21, 22. <hi>Receive ye the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> The caſe is the fame in <hi>Matthias, Saul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> as <hi>Acts</hi> 1.24. ond 13.2. and in thoſe which the Church made Overſeers or Biſhops, as <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. and <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11. and we have no reaſon at all to doubt, but that the Spirit doth as truly, tho' not ſo viſibly aſſiſt at the preſent Ordaining of Miniſters, as then ſince the Church Prays for, and bids them receive the Holy Ghoſt for the Office and Work of a Prieſt in the Church of God, now committed to ſuch by the Impoſition of Hands. And ſince many ſay that the Goſpel-Prieſthood is left open to all that will enter it without any further Ceremony, than a geting up and Ride, or a jumping from the Shop-board to the Pulpit or Desk. Now to the ſober Conſideration of ſuch, I Humbly recommend the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Particulars, as <hi>Firſt,</hi> Since St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſetting down the Nature of a Church, Stiles it the Body of Chriſt, where he means not a Similar Body, ſuch as <hi>Fire, Air,</hi> and <hi>Water,</hi> where all the parts are alike, and perform the ſame Office: But a Body conſiſting of Diverſity of Organs for ſeveral Faculties, and Operations, ſuch a Body as is not one Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, but many knit together with Unity and Charity, as with a band of Health, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. deſigned to Manifeſt that in the Church of Chriſt; it's as Monſtrous and Impoſſible for all he Teachers or Governours, as for the Body to be all Tongue or Eye: And that it is as Prepoſterous,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:134553:7"/>
and Deſtructive for all Promiſcuouſly to thruſt themſelves into the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, when the Spirit moves as for the Members of a Mans Body to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert their Natural Scituation, and all to preſs into the ſame Place; nay, beſides if according to ſome Mens Fancies, Abilities, be all that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to make a Clergy-man or Teacher, then it's highly reaſonable to make due inquiry into thoſe, ſo as to be duly and truly informed of their Nature and Reality. Now what Abilities ſoever any can pretend unto muſt either be infuſed, or acquired: If any then aſſume the Office of a Teacher, meerly upon the pretence of infuſed Abilities, or extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Gifts, then it's juſt with the Apoſtles to put them upon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch by that ſort of Teſtimony, which was ever required in ſuch a Caſe, to ſhew them by working ſome Miracles: For if ſuch bold Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders are to be Credited upon their own bare Word, how eaſily then will every confident Creature, only by rubbing their Forehead with Braſs, pretending extraordinary Gifts and Abilities; ſo by a meer bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Cozen, the Silly and Ignorant; do belye the Holy Ghoſt, from whom all real Gifts come, and conſequently deſtroy all Order in the Church, but we are commanded not to believe every Spirit, but to try them whether they be of God, ſince the Charge which is undertaken is no leſs than the cure of Souls: For the great Shepherd would not have his Sheep to wander up and down, (leaſt they go aſtray and be loſt) without any to feed them: You know what a ſtrict Command he laid upon <hi>Peter</hi> to feed his Sheep and Lambs, and which he Faithfully Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and Exhorted his fellow Elders or Miniſters to do the like, as 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5 1, 2. <hi>Feed the Flock of God, which is among you, taking the over-ſight thereof, not by conſtraint, but willingly: Not for filthy Lucre, but of a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Mind.</hi> Now if theſe who are ſo forward to take upon them the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial Office, would maturely revolve that it brings with it a charge of Souls, of which one Day they muſt give an Account, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This might perhaps not a little Cool their Heat, and the due Apprehenſion of the weightineſs of the Burthen would allay the Preſumption of their Abilities: Nor will it leſs deſerve a ſerious Conſideration, that if all have a right to the Miniſtry, then all have a right to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by it, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> proves from the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> inſtancing in the Ox and Labourer, the one not to be muzled, and the other worthy of his Hire: So arguing from common Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that ſince Spirituals were Miniſtred unto them, it's no great matter if they reap their Temporals; ſince as he concludes thoſe that Preach the Goſpel muſt live by it: A double Portion both of reſpect and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance being due to them, as 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19. to free them from the diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting Troubles of the World, enabling them to the oblidging Offices of Charity and Alms-Deeds, as to be not only apt to Teach, but given to Hoſpitality, which Conſideration, if the Pluraliſts will not have regard to, it's hoped, and wiſhed the Grand Council will, and make as good and wholſome Proviſion for Pluralities of Parſonages as are for Wives, and put a reſtraint upon the Overſeers or Elders of the Church, to make them for the future more Provident, as not to admit more to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, than they are indeed bound (tho' are not yet willing to maintain) and that an Eye be had towards Perſonal Perfections, as well as Abilities, and Honeſty of Deſcent, as well as Probity of Manners, and not to make Prieſts of the loweſt for Intereſt or Favour. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Nothing will ſerve ſome, but they muſt and will be Teachers, and through either an
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:134553:7"/>
Envious Faction, or a Miſtaken Zeal, they will detain that which is due, or be Fingering the hallowed Cenſor, and the Holy Fire. I leave ſuch to the Conſideration of their Anceſtors, <hi>viz. Corah, Dathan, Abiram,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah;</hi> Firſt for Inſtruction, and then for Afrightment, for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Inconveniences have befallen: And conſequently will unavoidably attend both Church and State by this, as <hi>Firſt,</hi> They let ſome Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous of their Abilities, to take upon them to become Teachers, has proved, and will again make even Preaching it ſelf; which many in this Age account the <hi>All</hi> of Religion, to become Weak and Contemptable, by being expoſed to all the Incongruities, Follies, Dotages, and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Ignorant, and Confident, of the Crafty and Deceitful, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Scripture it ſelf our only Rule, to be Hourly liable to ſuch Freakiſh and Will Expoſitions, as will make it moſt unlike it ſelf, and leaſt able to be that, which it was deſigned, <hi>viz.</hi> a compleat Rule of Faith, and Converſation, Truth, and Holineſs. And that there is more than a poſſibility of what I ſpeak, thoſe have ſufficiently informed us, who have Expounded the Scripture as their Humours and Wills would have it ſpeak; by Commenting Upon the Laws and Commands, till they left in them no Obligation; making God's Word ſpeak according to their Intereſt or Paſſions, and ſo expoſe Religion to perpetual Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions. And <hi>Secondly</hi> ſuch doings will have but little influence upon the Peace, and ſafety of the State to God: For when every one hath a liberty to teach what, and whom he pleaſeth: We may conclude from the Natural Pride of Men, that each will deſire to raiſe a Sect, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Head of a Party, over whoſe Conſciences when they have once got a competent Power, it will not be long till they have both their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and Fortunes at their Devotion; then their gathered Churches will be ſoon train'd into an <hi>Army:</hi> There being no fitter Materials of New Troops, than new Proſelites, who being imployed in the firſt warmth and briskneſs of their Zeal, will not ſtick at any attempt tending to the advancement of their Way, and to the Removal of whatſoever obſtructs their Deſign: And tho' the pretence of all this be Conſcience, and Zeal for the Lord, the removal of Abuſes, and the publick Welfare: Yet every Malecontent will help to the increaſe of the Cry: So that all the Sons of Ambition, Coveteouſneſs, Envy, and Revenge will emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty themſelves into the Faction; and thoſe who leaſt care for Religion, will then make it their pretext to ruin that which is Eſtabliſhed, and therewith the State: The ſad Truth of which Obſervation, dear bought Experience hath and now doth every where atteſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Third</hi> Command or Ordinance, which the great Apoſtle places before the laſt mentioned in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. The Doctrine of Baptiſms, which is an initial Principle, and fundamental Point of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: And ſince, as Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> ſaith, p. 2. There are, and have been, many which have, and do maintain divers Errors and Opinions, even for ſome long time; ſome now taking ſuch Opinions up only upon truſt, and without conſulting or adviſing with the Learned, entertains them as ſure and certain: Now to free thoſe from their former miſtakes, and conſequently from their Errors; I know of no other way than wholly to forſake theſe Doctrines, ſucked in with their Mothers Milk, which are turned to natural Food and Nouriſhment, and totally adhere to the Pure and Unerring Word of God, and not bring Hearts to it prepoſeſt with Doctrines and Opinions learned of their Grannums, but to come with Hearts and Conſciences free, and not pre-ingaged, in all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:134553:8"/>
Meekneſs, Uprightneſs, and Simplicity of Heart, to hear what the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Jeſus, with his faithful and true Witneſſes, <hi>viz.</hi> the Apoſtles have, and do ſay, touching the Point, and ſo receive and believe that alone, tho' never ſo differing from the Opinions and Doctrines of ſome, nay, of many: Tho' ſuch are and may be offended at it; yet I have choſe rather to build on the clear Word, tho' alone, than on any blind Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures, tho' magnified and embraced by many. Thus far Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> to p. 5. So as he further ſaith, In my inquiry, meeting with that place in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. where the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the Doctrine not only of Baptiſm, but Baptiſms in the plural number, which made me think and conclude, that there belongs to every adult Chriſtian, more than one Baptiſm; and what theſe then were, being ſuch neceſſary, principal and fundamental Points: I thought it my bounden Duty to enquire out, and with Mr. <hi>Dell,</hi> p. 8, 9. have gathered, and ſo concludes, that they are two diſtinct Baptiſms; the firſt by Water, to initiate and make us Members; the other by the Spirit, to ſtrengthen and confirm, ſo as to make us Children, and if Children, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> argues, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. then <hi>Heirs of God,</hi> and <hi>joynt Heirs with Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. The firſt called Water-Baptiſm, from St. <hi>John;</hi> the other being Fire-Baptiſm, from Chriſt, or his holy Spirit; both which are confirmed by St. <hi>Auguſt. contra. liter. Petil.</hi> 2. c. 39. where he ſaith, <hi>Alium fuiſſe</hi> Johannis <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmum alium Chriſti:</hi> And both abſolutely neceſſary to the Salvation of the Adult (tho' by reaſon of a dark and dim Glaſs, Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> could, or at leaſt would but ſee the one) for as our Saviour argues about other things, and this alſo; ſo may I withal obſerve, the one ought to be done, and the other not to be left undone: <hi>John</hi> 3.5. <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto thee, except a Man be Born of Water, and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God:</hi> And 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.20, 21. <hi>Eight Souls were ſaved by Water, the like Figure whereunto even Baptiſm doth now ſave us,</hi> &amp;c. And ſince that the Learned and Eloquent <hi>Apollos,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.25. <hi>inſtructed in the way of the Lord; ſpake and taught diligently the things of the Lord, knowing only the Baptiſm of</hi> John: Some of which things was undoubtedly Water-Baptiſm, and conſequently the Lord's, as well as <hi>John</hi>'s: Nay further, when St. <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 19.3, 4. found certain Diſciples which had only been Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, he Baptized them with the Holy Ghoſt, by laying his hands upon them, as verſe 6. Now this with Mr. <hi>Dell,</hi> p. 13. I muſt confeſs, being a ſecond Baptiſm, was not, as the Anabaptiſts fondly think, a Renewing, or Dipping them in Water, but only a lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his hands upon them, that the Holy Spirit might come to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power them. I think Mr. <hi>Dell,</hi> p. 14. has made an Objection, and drawn a Concluſion from it, which no wiſe Man either did, or could, ever make, or draw, <hi>viz. That</hi> John<hi>'s Doctrine was the ſame with Chriſt,</hi> therefore his Baptiſm the ſame: True, tho' the Doctrines were the ſame, yet this forced con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion could not follow, That their Baptiſms were: And p. 16. he ſaith, <hi>That</hi> John<hi>'s Baptiſm was brought in beſides the rite and manner of the Law, and ſo a ſign of a great Change to follow:</hi> It's but a miſtake which proceeded either from Wilfulneſs or Ignorance; for <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm was brought in, not beſides, but according to the rite and manner of the Law, for the <hi>Jews</hi> admitted all their Proſelites by it, and their Children alſo were waſhed, as well as circumciſed; neither was it a Sign, that it ſhould be changed, or left off, till the End; for only the intolerable and burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Cerimonies of the Law; ſuch as Circumciſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were to be aboliſhed: For <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, as he tells us, p. 17. is, tho' Weak, and Imperfect, yet very Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable; was Evangelical as well as Legal, being from Heaven, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.2. <hi>John</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:134553:8"/>
1.6, 33. ſo that God was, and is, the Author of this, as well as the other, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Publicans which received this Baptiſm, are ſaid to Juſtifie God, when as the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees and Lawyers that refuſed it, did then reject againſt themſelves, that is to their own hurt, the Counſel of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.29, 30. I wiſh there were none ſuch now; nay, Chriſt himſelf, who was Born under the Law, and ſo Circumciſed, to fulfil it; was ſubject to this Divine Inſtitution, of being <hi>Baptized</hi> with Water, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.13. not that he had any Sins to report of himſelf, but for us to imitate him in it, &amp; for our Sins that he might fulfill all <hi>Righteouſneſs, Mat.</hi> 3.15. and tho' Jeſus <hi>Baptized</hi> not himſelf, but his Diſciples more than <hi>John</hi>'s, as <hi>John</hi> 4.1, 2. true our Lord the chief Biſhop of our Souls (as our chief Biſhops now) <hi>Baptized</hi> none: It did not become him, neither doth it them, he had greater Work to do, ſo have they: He left it to his Apoſtles which were Subordinate, ſo do our Biſhops to the Subordinate Curates, as a thing ſtill needful to be done: No wonder then, if the great Apoſtle in ſuch a large Circuit or Dioceſs, as from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Illiricum,</hi> Acts 15.9. Baptized no more than two or three Believing Families; ſince he had a greater Work to do than lay that Foundation, which was laid by Subordinate Miniſters. So as (he ſaith) <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. &amp; 2. therefore leaving the Principles of the Doctrine of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> let us go on unto Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, not laying again the Foundation of Repentance, Faith, the Doctrine of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now tho' <hi>Water-Baptiſm</hi> gives not the, yet it initiates into the Church, and makes Members in order to be <hi>Baptized</hi> by the Spirit, to become Children, as <hi>Acts</hi> 19. and tho' it doth not give Kepentance, and Remiſſion to be Happy; yet it's in order to theſe: Infants indeed having never committed any actual Sins, have no need of Repentance, only of Remiſſion for their Originnl Sin, which is done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by the Blood of Chriſt, which the Water repreſents. So that if they Dye in their Infancy, they are undoubtedly Happy: So that contrary to Mr. <hi>Dell</hi>'s <hi>Ipſe dixit,</hi> in pages 26. 29. and 28. <hi>Water-Baptiſm</hi> both was, and is abſolutely neceſſary, and to continue till the end, ſo to make Infants dying before they commit actual Sins; and alſo the Adult, which is Born again of Water as well as of the Spirit; yea, of both, to make I ſay, ſuch Eternally Happy, as the Lord himſelf has aſſured us, <hi>John</hi> 3.5. ſo to paſs by his empty and frivilous Objections; where in the 3d. he has ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf a Phariſee, p. 29, 30. I'll only take notice of the Weak and Impertinent Anſwers he makes to the 5th, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That it is meant of Material Water, is Manifeſt from the Coplative and with the Enſuing Verſe. <hi>That which is Born of the Fleſh is Fleſh,</hi> to which the Water-Baptiſm belongeth, <hi>but that which is Born of the Spirit is Spirit,</hi> which is not improperly call'd a Second Baptiſm or New Birth, by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the Adult: But he further Objects, p. 34. Saying, <hi>Then upon the ſame ground Material Fire, in</hi> Matth. 3.11. <hi>as well as Material Water is meant in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited Text, which is abſurd.</hi> To which <hi>I</hi> Anſwer, To be Baptized with the Holy Ghoſt and with Fire, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11. Being an Hebraiſm, denotes only the Efficacy cy of the Holy Spirit, ſince at <hi>Penticoſt,</hi> the holy Spirit appeared unto them in ſhape of <hi>Cloven Tongues, like as of Fire,</hi> as <hi>Acts</hi> 2.3. So <hi>Infants</hi> which have committed no actual Sin, by being <hi>waſhed</hi> or <hi>baptized</hi> with <hi>Water,</hi> are like to the eight Souls in <hi>Noah</hi>'s Ark, ſaved, as it appears from 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.20, 21. and p. 36. he ſaith, <hi>That our Soviour, in that Commiſſion, bid them not Baptize or Dip them in cold Water, as</hi> John <hi>did, but into the Name of God.</hi> And p. 38. <hi>That tho' their Lord had given them a Form, yet was not ſince as we ever heard, or read of, any where elſe uſed by the Apoſtles;</hi> and that <hi>St.</hi> Paul <hi>baptizing but two or three Families, yet eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many Churches, whoſe Members were never waſhed at all by Water.</hi> And p. 42. <hi>probably moſt Apoſtles did the like;</hi> Seeing that Chriſt's Baptiſm included <hi>John's,</hi> and was ſufficient without it; and that there's but one Baptiſm, from <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.20.</p>
            <p>All this is but an Ipſe Dixit, without any Reaſon or Proof; the contrary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th manifeſtly appear in every particular, for all which the Apoſtles baptized were by the ſame Form in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, &amp;c. as Acts 19.5. Nor as we read did they ever Lay their Hands upon any Member as to be Baptized by the Spirit, but what were either before or after Baptized with Water, as Acts 10.43, 44. <q>Can any forbid Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that theſe ſhould not be Baptized which have received the Holy Ghoſt as well as we; and he commanded them to be Baptized in the Name of the Lord.</q> So that you may underſtand that the Baptizing by the Spirit was not ſufficient; but the Baptiſm of the Water muſt be added. True, St. Paul tells us. Epheſ. 1.5. That there's but one Baptiſm. Anſw. No more there is but one Man, but he conſiſts of two neceſſary parts, viz. Fleſh and Spirit: ſo is Baptiſm ſaid to be one, where our Saviour explains it thus in John 3.6. ſaying, <q>That which is born of the Fleſh is Fleſh, and that which is born of the Spirit is Spirit.</q> Therefore to be Chriſtians let us take the Apoſtles ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to 2 Cor. 7.1. Having therefore theſe Promiſes by Water and the Spirit to be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:134553:9"/>
found Members and Children, viz. Sons and Daughters, let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of the Fleſh and Spirit, perfecting Holineſs in the Fear of God. And ſince as St. Peter, Acts 2.39. aſſures us, That the Promiſe is to, us, and alſo to our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and to all that are afar off, even to as many as the Lord our God ſhall call. And ſince there are others which differing with (and diſſenting from) our Church, do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to obſerve and walk in all the Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord, ſo as be thought at leaſt blameleſs; which alas I find being ſeduced with popular Examples, have unwarily imbibed a groundleſs Prejudice againſt all the Children of Chriſtian Parents; which as I humbly conceive has been cauſed by not knowing, or want of Ephod, and Terephim among them, ſo not underſtanding the Scriptures which they have been apt to wreſt, but yet I hope not to their Childrens, tho' it to their own hurt: And that which they have grounded their Error on, is on Mat. 28.19. and ſome others, which mentions Teaching before Baptizing; and that we have no poſſitive Command for Initia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Infants as under the Law; and that we have neither Precept nor a Primitive Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent for ſo doing.—To which I Anſwer, That in that Commiſſion, Chriſt had a more peculiar regard to the Perſons to whom the Apoſtles were ſent, which were ignorant Superſtitions and prophane, therefore he mentions ſuch Qualifications antecedant to Baptiſm: for it was not fit that ſuch ſhould be admitted to a Covenant of Grace, and Reconciliation with God, till they with Abraham were converted and reclaimed, and underſtood the Covenant, and then (as he was Circumciſed) they to be Baptized. In ſhort, the matter was this; The Adult were firſt to be made Diſciples by a ſaving Faith, the caſe of the Children was diſtinct to be conſidered afterwards; when their Parents were not only Converted, but well grounded, or ſettled; and then alſo the Church judged it ſafeſt to take Proxies or Sureties, viz. ſome Old, and ſteady Converts, leſt the Parents Apoſtatizing, as they often did, and ſo the Children being under their Tuition, its preſumed that they would have the ſame Principles and Perſwaſion of the Parents Apoſtatized; then the Proxies took care and trained them up in the Chriſtian Faith: And thus Infants, as to the Covenant and Privileges, are accounted in the ſtate and right with their Parents. Therefore as the Children of Unbelievers upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count may in ſome caſes be ſaid to be partakers of their Parents Infidelity, ſince they are like to be brought up in it; and for that Reaſon they are denyed Baptiſm; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they are capable, and may be admitted where there is ſufficient Satisfaction given to the Church, that they ſhall be educated in the Chriſtian Religion; for it would be prepoſterous to admit ſuch into a Religion which they were never likely to be inſtructed in afterwards. Now when Circumciſion was thrown off, which was not at the firſt, then in all probability began the Jews to Start the caſe of Infants admiſſion, who by Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion were admitted, but that being aboliſhed, their privilege would be lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>: And theſe Abſurdities would have naturally followed; as Frſt, That Infants under the New Covenant were in a far worſe condition than thoſe under the Old; for they were entred. Secondly, That the Priviledges under the Goſpel were to Infants ſtraiter and narrower than thoſe under the Law, which would be abominable. 3dly, If it was God's Will that Infants under the Goſpel ſhould be reckoned as out of his Covenant, which before were in it, then it muſt follow that our Saviour was forgetful, and unfaithful to his Church, in that he never acquainted her with this alteration, which is alſo both baſe and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd; Nay, and this might juſtly raiſe Clamours and Complaints in the Jewiſh Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſo as to hinder the bringing in of their Parents. Indeed I muſt confeſs that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving and Repentance in the Adult, are abſolutely neceſſary, where Infidelity and Iniquity are found, as in Abraham; yet this doth not prove that the Infants of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers were, and are to be excluded, becauſe they cannot actually believe; yea, they are rather to be included and baptized, as Iſaac was Circumciſed: for the Scripture in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates that the Innocency of harmleſs Babes (whoſe Original Guilt is done away by Chriſt) who have not by actual Tranſgreſſion offended: ſuch innocency is as pleaſing to God, and as agreeable a Qualification for the admiſſion of ſuch to a Covenant of Grace and Mercy, by ſealing it with the not Intollerable, but Eaſie Seal of Baptiſm, as either the Faith of an Actual Believer, or the Repentance of the Penitent; this may be illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by Examples, which I ſhall own omit. What if Infanss do not as under the Law underſtand the Covenant, verily that is no bar: for if we were but as wiſe in Spirituals as in Temporals, we find it in no wiſe diſagreeable to Reaſon that Infants are bound in Covenants to the future Performance of Conditions which they at preſent know nothing of, nor can be capable of performing till they come to Age. This is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in Wills, in ſettling Eſtates on Infant-Heirs, having Guardians, &amp;c. But you'll ſay the Covenant is not the ſame.—Anſw. It's the ſame in Subſtance, tho' not in the Accidents. True, it differs in this; The firſt being in Works, had Circumciſion for its Seal: The laſt of Grace, which has Baptiſm for its. Acts 2.39. For the Promiſes is to us and our Children, which that we may embrace, God grant for Chriſt's ſake: Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:134553:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
